the case for other medicines where, such as Zolgens,
where we have it, Visma. But while the dose is changing, of course, the underlying gene therapy
is the same. So that is our assumption for all of those medicines. Cool. Many thanks.
Thank you. Your next question comes from the line of Michael Leuchten from Jefferies. Please go ahead.
Thank you for taking the follow-up. A question from Moco, please. The gross margin is pressured by
negative mixed effect, obviously. That is partly driven by
the genetic side of it. So, I'm going to ask you a question. So, I'm going to ask you a question
and partly by the new products having payaways. Is there a scale factor in here that we should
take into consideration as we think about the first half, second half of the year,
or is the gross margin just plain and simple, mixed driven?
Yeah. So, I think there is, as you rightly said, I think there's two things at play here. If we
look at Q1, the overall decrease in the margin is 4.1%. Three percentage points of that comes from
R&D.
And a percentage point comes from the GX impact on gross margin. Now, GX impact on gross margin,
pretty much, I think if we take 2025 as a base, pretty much H2 base is what you guys should model
going into this year, and that should be the base. And as far as R&D is concerned, I think we
have to take into account not just the avidity deal that we did, but we also did three other
pretty significant deals in terminal.
So, in Q1, all of these three deals plus one month of avidity is incremental, and going forward,
I think part of it is already in the base. So, the incremental R&D spend would start to run off.
Thank you. Next question.
Thank you. Your next question comes from the line of Thibaut Vaudelin from
Robin Stanley. Please go ahead.
Yes, thank you. Just a question on your comments on Votoplum and the potential discussion with
FDA on the Phase 2. We had the phase 2 data some time ago. Have you seen anything new in the
full data, open label extension, that makes you more confident on the potential for the FDA to
accept a path for approval?
Yeah, I think, as I said, we feel like the results that we've seen,